Guide to the Robert Chapman Bates Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Chapman Bates papers
1908-1943
MS 833
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
(21 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, notebooks, school papers, photographs, and memorabilia. The major part of the papers is made up of family correspondence (1908-1942) most of which consists of letters from Bates to his family written from boarding school and during his travels abroad. Also included are thirteen notebooks compiled while he was a graduate student in early French and Italian literature at Yale University.
Bates, Robert Chapman, 1901-1942
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Colonel and Mrs. William G. Bates, 1943, and C. B. Hogan, 1954.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Family Correspondence. II. General Correspondence. III. Personal Papers.
Biographical / Historical
ELIJAH BATES, 1770-1850
Elijah Bates, the eldest child of Captain Nathaniel and Hannah Bates, of (East) Granville, Massachussetts, and grandson of John and Edith Bates, of Durham, Connecticut, was born in Granville on July 27, 1770. His mother was a daughter of Jonathan and Abigail (White) Church. Isaac C. Bates (Yale 1802) was a first cousin.
He studied law with Judge Tapping Reeve in Litchfield, Connecticut and also in the office of Joseph Lyman (Yale 1783), of Westfield.
He established himself in practice in Westfield, which adjoins his native town, but from the first indulged a passion for agricultural pursuits, which interfered seriously with his professional success.
He was one of the foremost in the enterprise of opening a good highway from Westfield to Albany, and did much of the work in his vicinity at his own expense.
As a citizen he was public spirited and enterprising; one of the kindest of neighbors and most honest of men.
He was a member of the State Senate for one or more sessions.
For many years he limited his professional labors mainly to the winter months, devoting the summer to his favorite out-of-door pursuits; and in 1825, when his elder son began law studies, he made his retirement final.
He died in Westfield on February 4, 1850, in his 80th year.
He married, on June 15, 1800, Mary (or Polly), eldest daughter of Dr. Israel Ashley (Yale 1767), of Westfield, who died on July 10, 1845, aged 75 years.
Their children were two sons and one daughter, all of whom survived their parents. The elder son was graduated at Yale in 1825.
(Yale College Class of 1794, Biographical Sketches)
* * * * *
ISAAC CHAPMAN BATES, 1779-1846
Isaac Chapman Bates was a son of Colonel Jacob and Ruth Bates of Granville, Massachusetts, and a first cousin of Elijah Bates (Yale 1794). His mother was a daughter of Phineas Robinson of Granville, and widow of Isaac Chapman, who died in November, 1776. He was born in Granville on January 23, 1779, and was prepared for College by the Rev. Dr. Timothy M. Cooley (Yale 1792), who had married his half-sister. An excellent scholar in College, and distinguished as a writer and speaker, he was chosen to deliver the Valedictory Oration at graduation.
He studied law in New Haven with Seth P. Staples (Yale 1797), and afterwards with Judge Samuel Hinckley (Yale 1781), of Northampton, where he was admitted to the bar at the May term in 1805. An oration which he delivered on the fourth of July brought him at once into favorable notice, and he soon took a prominent rank among the practitioners in Western Massachusetts. His striking personal advantages,––a commanding presence, a rich, silvery voice, and graceful address, joined with a power of manly and lucid argument, made him especially effective as an advocate before a jury.
He was not only much employed in professional, but also in civil life. In 1808-1809, and once subsequently, he was a Representative in the General Court of Massachusetts; and in December, 1827, he took his seat as a Representative in Congress (anti-Jackson), where he was continued for eight years, and then declined a re-election. After this he served again as a member of the State Legislature, and was for two years in the Governer's Council. He served as a presidential elector in 1836 and 1840.
In January, 1841, he was elected to the Senate of the United States, to fill the vacancy caused by the resignation of the Hon. John Davis (Yale 1812), who had just been chosen Governor. When his term had expired, he was elected Senator for the next six years (1841-1847), but did not live to finish his term. He had been much overworked in the discharge of his duties, and in February, 1845, made an able speech, opposing the admission of Texas. Though ill, he appeared in his seat for the last time on the last day of that month, and he died in Washington on March 16, in his 67th year.
His colleague in the Senate, Daniel Webster, in announcing his death, paid a high tribute to his ability and eloquence.
He married, on September 21, 1807, Martha, the eldest child of Judge Samuel Henshaw (Harvard 1773) and Martha (Hunt) Henshaw, of Boston and Northampton, who died in Northampton on November 9, 1874, in her 92nd year.
They had five daughters and three sons. The eldest daughter married the Rev. Fordyce M. Hubbard (Williams Coll. 1828); the second daughter married the Hon. Samuel H. Walley (Harvard 1826); the third daughter married Lewis J. Dudley (Yale 1838); the fourth daughter married Haynes H. Childon (Amherst Coll. 1843); and the youngest married first, Charles F. Snmith (Amherst 1838), and secondly, John A. Dana (Yale 1844). The eldest son was graduated here in 1833; the youngest died in infancy.
(Yale College Class of 1802, Biographical Sketches, page 473)
* * * * *
ROBERT CHAPMAN BATES, 1901-1942
Robert Chapman Bates, assistant professor of French in Yale University, was born on 27 July 1901 in New York City, son of William Graves and Amy Rowan (Scott) Bates. He attended Choate School, Philips Andover Academy, and Yale College (B.A., 1923). After graduation he worked with the Guaranty Trust Company, New York City, from 1923 to 1925. He registered in the Yale Graduate School, Department of Romance Languages, in 1925 and received the Ph.D. in 1930. He was instructor in French from 1930 to 1937, assistant professor from 1937 to 1942, and fellow of Jonathan Edwards College from 1933 to 1942. He edited Le conte dou barril (1932) and L'hystore Job (1937), two medieval French poems. Bates died at forty-one on 1 December 1942 of chronic pulmonary insufficiency. For more information see Yale University Obituary Record, 1942-1943, pp. 129-130.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, diaries, notebooks, school papers, photographs, and memorabilia. The major part of the papers is made up of family correspondence (1908-1942) most of which consists of letters from Bates to his family written from boarding school and during his travels abroad. Also included are thirteen notebooks compiled while he was a graduate student in early French and Italian literature at Yale University.
Boarding schools -- United States; Literature -- History and criticism; Europe -- Description and travel; Bates, Robert Chapman, 1901-1942; Choate School; Phillips Academy; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Dept. of French
- Family Correspondence, Series I
  - Family Correspondence, 1896-1918 October (Box 1, Folder 1 - 7)
  - Family Correspondence, 1918 November-1921 June (Box 2, Folder 8 - 14)
  - Family Correspondence, 1921 October-1925 (Box 3, Folder 15 - 21)
  - Family Correspondence, 1925 September-1928 September (Box 4, Folder 22 - 29)
  - Family Correspondence, 1928 August-1932 (Box 5, Folder 30 - 36)
  - Family Correspondence, 1933-1937 December (Box 6, Folder 37 - 42)
  - Family Correspondence, 1938-1942 (Box 7, Folder 43 - 49)
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, Series II
  - A-Z (Box 8, Folder 1 - 3)
  - Allison, J.M.S., 1935-1940 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Beedan, Joseph, 1922-1934 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Buck, Allan, 1933-1939 (Box 8, Folder 6 - 8)
  - Cannon, Beeckman, 1932-1942, undated (Box 8, Folder 9 - 10)
  - Childs, W.C., 1935-1942 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Converse, Allan D., 1932-1937 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Dilsworth, J.R., 1936-1939 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Foord, Archibald S., 1934-1935 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Furniss, J.P. and W.T., 1927-1942 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Gillespie, R.M., 1925-1963 (Box 9, Folder 16 - 19)
  - Hartman, Herbert, 1923-1937 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Hogan, C.B., 1928-1940 (Box 9, Folder 21 - 23)
  - Jackson, J.H., 1935-1936 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Kenway, Bud, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Leais proio, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Locraft, T.M., 1927-1941 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Miller, Hunt, 1933-1935 (Box 9, Folder 28 - 29)
  - Negley, Albert S.B., 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Olmstead, A.W., 1942 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Parkev, Tom, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Peterson, F.A., 1935-1942 (Box 10, Folder 33 - 34)
  - Pope, G.D., 1933-1942 (Box 10, Folder 35 - 36)
  - 'S', 1932-1935 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Sneidthacher, Augustus B., 1882 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Tinker, Chauncey B., 1921-1941 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Wallace, Hugh C., 1928-1941 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - White, R.M. II, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Yale College, 1930-1942 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Unidentified, 1922-1942 (Box 10, Folder 43 - 44)
  - RCB to miscellaneous, 1936-1943 (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous to Mrs. Bates, 1919-1943 (Box 10, Folder 46)
- PERSONAL PAPERS, Series III
  - Bible (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Diaries (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Box 11, Folder 5 - 6)
  - Student papers (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Tributes (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Yale University
    - Exams (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - General papers (Box 12, Folder 10 - 12)
    - Graduate school notebooks, 1925-1927 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Graduate school notebooks, 1926-1928 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Graduate school notebooks, 1927-1928 (Box 15, Folder 15)